Guide to the Polytechnic History and Milestones Collection RG.021
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Polytechnic History and Milestones Collection
1853-2011
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
RG.021
12 Linear Feet 6 boxes: 4 cartons, 2 oversize
Biographical / Historical
The items in the collection originally existed in serval "historic Poly" groupings in the Poly Archives.
One group of items in this collection, along with five rare books, were uncovered from a locked red safe in the Poly Archives in October, 2013. Vague directions to the combination lock prevented access to the items for a number of years. Once the safe was opened, it was decided to re-house the items in a way that would ensure access and provide better preservation than the small metal safe.
Another group of items was stored in binders that did not meet preservation standards. These items were re-housed into acid-free folders and boxes.
Combining these two groupings into one collection created a unified collection of early Polytechnic documents, historical overviews of Polytechnic, and descriptions of milestone (100 and 150 year) anniversaries.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Items are arranged into ten series by subject. Items within series are arranged by subject, chronologically.
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection include original stock certificates and charters of the university, meeting minutes, ledgers, the "golden books" of honorary degree recipients, floor plans of the original buildings, and gifts to the university. This collection covers a wide range of dates, from plans for the university in 1853 to the most recent charter amendment in 2011.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials.
- Series I: Historical Publications and Overviews
  - First Quarter Century of the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute (3 copies), 1880 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Meeting Minutes, 1853-1879 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Stockholders, 1855-1889 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Announcement of Opening, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Circular, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Opening, Stockholders, and Circular, 1855-1857 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Statement to the New York Regents, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Invitation from the Trustees of the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Catalogs, 1857, 1866, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - First Quarter Century of the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute and Packer Collegiate Institute, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Polytechnic Institute Accounting, 1889, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Polytechnic: A Monthly Magazine of College New and Literature, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn: Its Past, Present, and Future, circa 1907 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn for City, State, and Nation, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn for City, State, and Nation, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Story of Polytechnic and Its Service to the Public, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn Illustrated in Sixteen Pictures, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Sixty-Seven Years Old, 1921, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Polytechnic History and Traditions, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - A Bit of Polytechnic History and a Few Statistics, circa 1929 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Story of Poly, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Polytechnic Menu for N.Y. Central Dining Cars, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Building Fund Report, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Report of the President with Historical Review, 1940-1958 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Unpublished History of Polytechnic, 1890-1290, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Ad Hoc Planning Committee Draft Report: PIB History and Origins, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - A Brief History of Polytechnic, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Notes from the Institute Archives, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - A Challenge to Excellence, circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Towards the Technological University: The Story of Polytechnic Institute of New York, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Polytechnic University Fact Sheet, circa 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Polytechnic University: History and Tradition, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Polytechnic Timeline, Milestones, Gifts, and Inventors, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Bugliarello Memo to Faculty Re: Poly's History, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Historical Outlines, 1994-2002 and 2005 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Polytechnic Site: Historical Antecedents, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - History of Polytechnic, 1853-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, 1897-1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute First Annual Report of the Board of Trustees (bound volume), 1854 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - The Story of Poly (bound volume), 1940 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn Organization and Roll of Membership, 1889 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Polytechnic Corporation Notebook, 1973-1988 (Box 3, Item 4)
- Series II: Stockholders and Stock Certificates
  - Subscriptions, Academy for Boys, Brooklyn, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stockholders, 1856 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Stockholders Correspondence, 1869-1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stockholders Correspondence, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn Female Academy Stock Certificates, 1845 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Stock Certificates, 1854 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series III: Original Site and Building Records
  - Livingston Street Building Floor Plans, 1855-1890 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Polytechnic Institute Floor Plans, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Deed to Polytechnic Institute Correspondence, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - List of Court Street Rentals, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Department of City Works, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Brooklyn Department of Buildings, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Brooklyn Department of Buildings, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Edison Electric Illuminating Company, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 99 Livingston Street Site History, circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 99 Livingston Street Site Sketches, circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series IV: Charters and Articles of Association
  - Charter of the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (bound), 1890 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Amendments to the Charter, 1930 and 1939, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Object 3)
  - Charter Amendment correspondence, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Charter Amendment, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Charter Amendment, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Charter Amendment, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Charter Amendment, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Charter Amendment, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Charter Amendments, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Charter Amendment, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Charter Amendment, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Compilation of References to Charter from Corporation Minutes, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Photocopies of the Articles of the Association and various ledgers, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Exhibit of Early Polytechnic Documents, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Series V: Faculty
  - To the Memory of Elihu Spicer, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - In Memoriam: Harry Stanley Rogers, 1957 (Box 4, Item 2)
  - New York State Education Department, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Lectures and Demonstrations Offered by PIB to Students of High Schools, circa 1935 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn Scientific and Technological Publications: Evening Graduate Programs in the New York Metropolitan Region, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Summary of the Report of the Committee on Faculty Salaries, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Series VI: Students
  - Student Records and Correspondence, 1874-1890 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Certificates for Admission, circa 1920, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Scholarship and Employment record of Evening Students, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Events, 1856-1935 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Polytechnic Class Pins, 1893, 1896, 1899, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Basketball Schedule, 1911, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Dances and Banquets, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Mermaid Club, 1909-1912 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Mermaid Club Dance, 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Polytechnic Dramatic Association, 1910-1915 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Histories of Phi Lambda Upsilon and Tau Beta Pi, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - The Play Workshop, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Series VII: Milestone Celebrations
  - Centennial Celebrations Committee, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Centennial Celebration Dinner Program, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - One Hundredth Anniversary Invitation, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Centennial Celebration Program, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Proceedings of the Centennial Convocation, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Centennial Celebration Matchbooks, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Centennial Year Commencement Program, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Centennial Convocation Press Release, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Newsweek "Brooklyn Polytechnic: 1854-1953" (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Centennial Celebration Clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Brooklyn Poly Celebrates 100 Years, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Centennial Celebrations Mailing Lists, Greetings, Etc., 1955 (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Centennial Greetings, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Universitas Leodiensis MDCCCXVI, 1955 (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn: An account of the Educational Purposes and Development of the Institute during its first century, 1955 (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Sesquicentennial Convocation and Inauguration Invitations, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sesquicentennial Convocation and Inauguration Program, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Celebrating 150 Years Inaugural Gala, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sesquicentennial Medalist Ceremony, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Inspiration and Innovation Sesquicentennial Edition Compact Disc, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Changing the World: Chapters 1 and 2 Draft Manuscript, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Changing the World: Chapters 3 and 4 Draft Manuscript, 2004 (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Changing the World: Chapters 5 and 6 Draft Manuscript, 2004 (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Changing the World: Chapters 7 and 8 Draft Manuscript, 2005 (Box 6, Item 4)
  - Changing the World: Chapters 9, 10, and 11 Draft Manuscript, 2005 (Box 6, Item 5)
  - The Legend of Polytechnic University Outline Revised (Draft for Changing the World), 2004 (Box 6, Item 6)
  - Changing the World, Heather Walter's Notes, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Item 7)
  - Changing the World Draft, C. Hayes' Office, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Item 8)
  - Changing the World: The First 150 Years, 2005 (Box 6, Item 9)
  - Changing the World e-Book PDF on Compact Disc, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series VIII: Affiliated Institutions
  - Brooklyn Female Academy (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Poly Preparatory Country Day School, 1930, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Micellaneous College and City Buildings, 1883-1884 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - The African Wesleyan Methodist-Episcopal Church (Known as the Bridge Street AWME Church) Org. 1766 - Inc. 1818, 1980 (Box 5, Item 2)
  - The History fo the African Wesleyan Methodist Episcopal Church, Volume 2, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series IX: Negatives and Realia
  - Negatives, circa 1854 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Italiani-Congresso Ingegneri medal, 1883 (Box 6, Item 10)
  - Memorial Chemist Medals from BASF, 1978 (Box 6, Item 11)
  - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute Founded A.D. 1854 in frame, undated (Box 6, Item 12)
  - The Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn: To all unto whom these Presents shall come or may concern, GREETING in frame, undated (Box 6, Item 13)
- Series X: Polytechnic Honorary Degrees ("Golden Books")
  - Golden Book, 1930-1969 (Box 7, Object 1)
  - Golden Book, 1970-1981 (Box 7, Object 2)
  - Golden Book, 1997-2013 (Box 7, Object 3)
    Scope and Contents
    When originally processed, the honorary degree citations in the most recent Golden Book were from 2005-2013. In May 2023, Prof. Richard Thorsen donated addition original citations, which were added to the book. The citations now range from 1997-2013.
  - 16G Thumb Drive with Honorary Degree List (Box 7, Item 4)
    Custodial History
    Donated by Prof. Richard Thorsen in May 2023.
  - List of Honorary Degrees Conferred 1930-2013 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Duplicates of Honorary Degree Citations, 1997-2007, 1997-2013 (Box 7, Folder 2)